<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The loss of the soul the irreparable loss, opened and demonstrated ... in a sermon, on Matt. XVI, 26 / by T. Beverley.</title>
            <author>Beverley, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27616</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B2161</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20343</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11771263</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11771263</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48863</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27616)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48863)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 808:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The loss of the soul the irreparable loss, opened and demonstrated ... in a sermon, on Matt. XVI, 26 / by T. Beverley.</title>
                  <author>Beverley, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 29, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W. Marshall ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew XVI, 26 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Soul --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Salvation --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48863:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48863:1"/>
            <p>THE Loſs of the Soul, THE IRREPARABLE LOSS, Opened and Demonſtrated,</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. By the Excellency of the Soul.</item>
               <item>II. The Utter Incompetency of the World to Anſwer it.</item>
               <item>III. The Miſery of a Soul Loſt.</item>
               <item>IV. The Eternal Sting of that Queſtion, <hi>What ſhall a Man give in Exchange for a Lost Soul?</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>IN A SERMON, ON</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MATT.</hi> XVI. 26.</bibl>
               <p>What ſhall it profit a Man, if he gain the whole World, and loſe his own Soul; or what ſhall a Man give in exchange for his Soul?</p>
            </q>
            <p>By <hi>T. BEVERLEY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>W. Marſhall,</hi> at the Bible in <hi>Newgate-ſtreet,</hi> 1694. Where you may be ſupplied with moſt of Mr. <hi>Beverley</hi>'s, and Dr. <hi>Owen</hi>'s Works.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:48863:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48863:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Honourable Gentlemen, Supporting the Lords-Day Lecture in the Morning, at Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi>'s Meeting, near <hi>Fetter-Lane, London.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THere is no Apology to be made (my very Honoured) for the Confidence of my preſenting this Sermon to you, but the Tranſcendent Weight and Excellency of the Subject; and that wherever this Diſcourſe comes, your giving ſuch Encouragement to the Preaching the Goſpel of Chriſt, on which occaſion this Sermon was Preached, may be ſpoken of by it in <hi>Memorial</hi> of you, and of my own Grateful Senſe of my participation of your Favour and Good-will therein, who Acknowledg my ſelf most unworthy of any ſuch. I Acknowledg, I have <hi>Darkened</hi> the <hi>Counſels</hi> of ſo Great a Truth by <hi>Words without Knowledg;</hi> But who is <hi>ſufficient</hi> for it according to its Dignity? The <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets</hi> of this <hi>Wiſdom</hi> are <hi>double</hi> to All can be ſaid of it; But if there be any Thing ſpoken with the Evidence of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Truth, or in Any Meaſure (through Gracious Aſſiſtance) Worthy of it, or Acceptable to any of the Servants of Christ, or your ſelves in particular; I deſire most Humbly, it may by a proportion of Acceptance, be Transferred to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Kingdom of Christ, and the Line of Time to it, I have ſo laboured in; yet not I, but the Grace of Christ with me; For, if the Lord hath enabled his unworthiest Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to ſpeak in this Great Point aright, and according to his Word, and the Divine Reaſon of it, I hope it will hence
<pb facs="tcp:48863:3"/> appear, He hath Enabled me to give Good Heed to what I have ſpoken, and <hi>whereof</hi> I have <hi>Affirm'd,</hi> and on what grounds I have ſo Affirm'd concerning the Great Revolution of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> ſo near as 1697. and which I cannot but Humbly Look upon, as that Eſpecial Diſpenſation committed to me, and therein I magnify my Office. And ſo I commend All to Divine Influence, and Bleſſing, Preparing by this Diſcourſe for his Kingdom, and Aſſuring it thereby to us; And for all Bleſſings, and most Gracious Preſence of God with you in all your Stations, Action, and Conditions, eſpecially in Heavenly Places, and Things are the moſt unfeigned Supplications of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Honoured Gentlemen,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Moſt Humble Servant in that <hi>Everlasting Kingdom. T. BEVERLEY.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48863:3"/>
            <head>THE GREATNESS OF THE Loſs of a Soul: AND THAT There can be no Exchange found for it.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>MATT. XVI. 26.</bibl>
                  <p>For what is a Man Profited, if He Gain the whole World, and Loſe his own Soul? or what ſhall a Man give in Exchange for his Soul?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THIS Great <hi>Oracle</hi> of our Lord and Maſter, is indeed one of the chief <hi>Baſes,</hi> or Foundations of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſtianity; It is one of the Pillars, the <hi>Seven Pillars,</hi> on which <hi>Wiſdom hath Founded its Houſe, viz.</hi> That there is no Compariſon between the <hi>whole World,</hi> and the value and worth of an Immortal Spirit, conſidered, as in an Immortal State and Condition; an Immortal, Unchangeable, and Everlaſting <hi>Self:</hi> So that if a Man could Gain the <hi>whole World</hi> with the loſs of this <hi>Self,</hi> he could be no Gainer, becauſe that which ſhould enjoy all, is loſt. And further, He muſt be a loſer beyond all we can conceive or expreſs; for he will come to Rue, or dearly to Repent this Loſs: He will come even Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:48863:4"/> to cry out, <hi>What ſhall I give in exchange,</hi> or as a price of Redemption for my <hi>Loſt Soul?</hi> though I loſt it for a <hi>whole World</hi> gain'd by that loſs?</p>
            <p>This is expreſſed by our Lord, in ſo plain and familiar a way, and ſo ſhooting of it ſelf into the Univerſal Senſe, and Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of Mankind, Every one can weigh at this Scale and by this Beam, and caſt this Account; <hi>If thou be wiſe, thou ſhalt be wiſe for thy ſelf;</hi> But if <hi>thou ſcorneſt, thou alone ſhalt bear it,</hi> Prov. 9. Our great unhappineſs is this, That we have not, as I may call it, a Vital ſenſe, and Apprehenſion of it; ſuch a one, as that is, by which we Apprehend, State, and Value, or rather im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately feel, and are touch'd to the quick' (as we ſay) in all the concernments of the preſent Life, and ſelf preſervation in it.</p>
            <p>This Senſe we cannot have, but from the <hi>Spirit of Truth, lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into All Truth,</hi> by giving us a Vital Union to it, and with it; for tho' it be ſpoken Ten Thouſand times to us; tho' we cannot deny it; tho' we praiſe the Diſcourſes of it; yet we ſhall not elſe perceive ſuch Dints, and Impreſſions, ſuch alway accompanying Powers of it, as to Act according to it: Yet that I may preſent this Diſcourſe with all the advantages of Addreſs I can by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Aſſiſtance extend it to, and on which I moſt humbly pray the Benediction of the Father of <hi>Lights,</hi> of <hi>Spiints.</hi> I will firſt, by way of Preparation, and Entrance, Conſider theſe Four Things:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Who is He, that hath here ſpoken theſe words to all the World, to the whole Human Nature, eſpecially to all that are called Chriſtians, and among them, more eſpecially to thoſe, who are indeed his <hi>Friends,</hi> as he calls them in a like ſpeech, <hi>Luke</hi> 12. <hi>What is a Man profited, if he gain, &amp;c.</hi> It is even He, that as He is the great Lover of Souls, ſo He is the great Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſer and Redeemer of them; He that had computed, and knew the value of Souls, when He came to dye for them, to Humble Himſelf to the death of the Croſs, He weighed with Himſelf, what was the worth of theſe Immortal Beings, for which he came to dye; For as it is ſaid of <hi>Abner, Died Abner as a Fool dieth?</hi> Died He upon a ſmall or trivial an Account? How much more may we ſay of the <hi>Lord of Life and Glory?</hi> Did He come to dye on any low account? He knew what He came to dye for; He knew what the Immortal ſtate of Spirits is; the Greatneſs of the Happineſs on one ſide, of the Miſery on the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:48863:4"/> other. He knew then the Souls of all Men; of all that are now before him; He knew in a peculiar manner the Souls of his own, what the Miſery was He Redeemed them from, and the Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs alſo He Ranſomed them into. Now in the view, and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey of all this, and as giving the <hi>Account,</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks in another Caſe; which His Soul had ſought and found, He ſpake theſe words? <hi>What ſhall it profit a Man, if he gain the whole World, and loſe his Soul;</hi> and if he loſes his Soul, <hi>What ſhall he give in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change for it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We deferr this to every Wiſe and Honeſt Man; We allow this Honour to him, that He is able to ſpeak of the Things wherein he deals, according to their true worth and value. We give this Credit to Merchants that deal in Foreign Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities; to any great Purchaſer; we look upon his Judgment, and eſtimate as a Standard: Now He that knew above any in Heaven or Earth the price of Souls; He who is the ſingle and alone Purchaſer of Them, (For as to any other, <hi>The Redemption of Souls is Precious,</hi> and <hi>ceaſeth for ever,) ſaid this.</hi> And he is not only the Purchaſer, but the Creator and Supreme End of them, <hi>They were all created by him, and for him.</hi> Who then, as He, could <hi>Lift up his Hand,</hi> as it were, <hi>to Heaven,</hi> and ſay, <hi>What ſhall it profit a Man, if he gain the whole World, and loſe his own Soul; or what ſhall a Man give in exchange for it? He ſaw,</hi> and <hi>ſearched it out,</hi> and <hi>declared it</hi> from his own certain knowledg in the making Souls; and from his Experience in the Purchaſe of them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us obſerve, how our Lord lays us in one Scale what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is higheſt, even the uttermoſt that can be ſuppoſed, tho' it never has, or ſhall be attained; He does not ſpeak of a little thing, when he lays a Soul in the other Scale; but whatever can be ſuppoſed to Counter-ſway, or Counter-ballance a Soul; Suppoſe all the Honours, Profits, Pleaſures of the World could be gained at the price of a Soul, whatever the Covetous or the Ambitious, or Proud, the Senſualiſt, or Voluptuary do, or would roll themſelves in; Suppoſe a Man could have all this with all immaginable advantages; All this, ſaith our Lord, could not weigh againſt one Soul. We know, it is a very little of the World we adventure for, we engage our Souls for, There was never yet any Man that could ſay, He was Maſter of the whole World, and All Things in it; But ſuppoſe a Man could ſay, He had it, and upon the longeſt Term of Life, and at the higheſt Elevation, or Exaltation; yet if we believe Him, who
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48863:5"/> had all Reaſon to know it, All this were not to be named with a Soul: Nay, in <hi>Solomon's</hi> Judgment, they are not ſufficient to defray the Charges of Life, the <hi>Vanity</hi> and <hi>Vexation of Spirit</hi> that preſs upon this Life, in this ſtate of <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Miſery,</hi> one may ſay, it is <hi>Mortgaged under.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Foot of the Account, the Ballance of the Account, at the loweſt that can be given, is this, That a <hi>Man</hi> would not be <hi>profited, if he ſhould gain the whole World, and loſe his own Soul;</hi> All that he got by it would amount to juſt nothing: Our Lord Conveys it therefore under the ſhade of a Man Adventuring up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Sea, and getting how much ſoever can be ſuppoſed by the Adventure, and then his Life, Himſelf be caſt away; ſuppoſe it were a World in his Arms, What would ſuch a Man get? If that whereby we Taſte, Enjoy, Take in, whatever can be given into our poſſeſſion be loſt; All that <hi>whole World</hi> becomes immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately nothing to him. For, whoſe then ſhall that World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come? If <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays, <hi>Seeing there are many things that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe vanity,</hi> What is Man the better! How much more, if his <hi>whole</hi> becomes an abſolute Cypher, a Nothing to him, What can <hi>He be the better?</hi> This is experimental Truth. The Devil truely ſaid, <hi>Skin for skin, all that a Man hath would he give for his Life:</hi> This is true in the ſenſe and verdict of Nature; God therefore, the Great Arbiter of Life, hath this Bridle in the Mouth of the moſt <hi>Atheiſtic,</hi> the Fools, that ſay either in their <hi>Heart,</hi> or openly, <hi>There is no God,</hi> They are under this <hi>Deſpotic</hi> Abſolute Power, whatever they call it, they muſt dye, and they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſecure againſt, how ſoon! And this blanks all they can propoſe; <hi>Their Breath</hi> is at ſome ones Pleaſure, ſome Will, and Diſpoſe that is not their own, but above it, <hi>It goeth forth, and in that very day their thoughts periſh,</hi> concerning all things <hi>under the Sun;</hi> And this proportionably falls on all who are <hi>Rich towards themſelves, and not towards God,</hi> Luke 12. 21.</p>
            <p n="4">4. By theſe words of our Lord and Saviour, there will come a great and ſad review upon a Man's loſs of his Soul; There is a ſurvivor to this loſs; that will have an earneſt deſire to this Soul, to this Self again, that will cry out, Where is that Thing that I may find out to give in Exchange, as a Reprizal for my loſt, and undone Soul? And what is this Survivor, but the loſt and undone Soul it ſelf, reviewing, and looking back on it ſelf, as ſo loſt? So our Lord intends to intimate to us, by adding, as a Clap of Thunder, falling upon the Loſt ſtate of a Soul; <hi>What ſhall a Man give in Exchange for his Soul?</hi> The words are
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48863:5"/> ſpoken in a vehemency, or in a Paſſion of Anguiſh, Horror, and Deſpair, upon the ſenſe of ſo miſerable a Bargain.</p>
            <p>Were it not for this after Account, a Man might pleaſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in this, if he could <hi>Gain the whole World,</hi> or make ſome No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as it might ſeem, Acquiſt of it; That he had laid his Hand upon the Prize, as he ſaid; <hi>Hoc nobile Feci quod perii,</hi> I have this ſatisfaction, that I have brought what I deſired to paſs, though I periſh in it: But this ſo terrible Review, this ſo dear Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance will ſting and torment for ever; becauſe ſuch <hi>Exchange</hi> is not poſſible to be found; ſuch an <hi>Exchange</hi> is neither to be found above nor below, which a Man may give in <hi>Exchange for his Soul.</hi> For when our Lord ſays, <hi>What ſhall a Man give in Exchange for his Soul?</hi> It is as if he ſhould ſay, There is no ſuch Poſſible to be found.</p>
            <p>Here are two Queſtions then our Lord has put, which can no way be Anſwered, but by ſubmitting to his Advice, To loſe our Lives here that we may ſave them for ever, rather than to ſave them here and loſe them for ever; by being put upon the neceſſity of ſeeking an <hi>Exchange for our Souls</hi> that cannot be found.</p>
            <p>Theſe things being thus premiſed, I will now ſtate the ſenſe of the Words, and ſo lay down the Propoſition to be Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed.</p>
            <p>In ſtating the ſenſe of the Words, Three things are to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired into:
<list>
                  <item>1. What is meant by a <hi>Soul?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. What by a <hi>Soul loſt?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. What by an <hi>Exchange for a Soul loſt?</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That which is the ſhade and ſimilitude, under which the Lord conveys his Divine ſenſe of a Soul, is <hi>Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We know, all Taſt and Enjoyment is by the benefit of Life; If you take away Life, Man to all Things here in the World is a Carcaſs, or lump of Clay; He cannot enjoy: For the Body, by which the Soul had any enjoyment here is ſo, and it is no other than a dead Body, and ſo cannot enjoy; Put all you can upon a Dead Body, it is all one to it; All the Funeral Pomp and State in the World, it knows nothing of; It does not rejoyce in it; It is not at all pleaſed; It is all one to it, to be conveyed down in the greateſt ſilence to the Chambers of Darkneſs.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:48863:6"/>
            <p>So in the very ſame manner, Let a Man have all the World, yet if his Life be taken from him, all that World becomes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently a Cypher, a Nothing to him, a perfect Darkneſs; In the Verſe therefore before the Text, <hi>v.</hi> 25. the ſame word is uſed for <hi>Life,</hi> that is in this Verſe of the Text, <hi>v.</hi> 26 Tranſlated <hi>Soul. Whoſoever will ſave his Life, ſhall loſe it; and he that will loſe his Life for my ſake ſhall find it. Pſyche</hi> is the word uſed, the very ſame word, <hi>What is a Man priſited, if he ſhall gain the whole World, and loſe his own Life?</hi> For then the <hi>whole World</hi> is nothing to him. <hi>Or what ſhall a Man give in exchange for his Life?</hi> Becauſe it is ſo well known, All the World cannot buy back Life, if it be once gone. This is the Shade our Lord uſes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The word <hi>Soul</hi> is to be underſtood yet more ſtrictly and cloſely, for the very <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Immortal Spirit;</hi> becauſe that indeed is the very Power and Principle of Life in every one of us: It is not the Body, nay, it not that very Glorified Body of the Reſurrection; It is not that does primarily, or originally enjoy, or take in Happineſs; but it is that happy and bleſſed Spirit that ſhall be in that Glorified Body, and therefore the Apoſtle calls it a <hi>Spiritual Body;</hi> that is, a Body every way fitted for the Uſe, and to the Service of the Spirit: If any one therefore ſay to himſelf, I have a Being within me, that acts in all the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and Powers of my Body, that ſees in my Eye, and hears in my Ear, that taſts, and feels, and apprehends all Things, and has the whole power of Reſentment within it ſelf, either as to Happineſs or Miſery; and that this Being ſurvives even to Eternity, a Reſenting Being, that carries all our Reſentment, our Apprehenſion; If this Being that cannot dye, be loſt, it muſt be loſt, by loſing that which is the Life of it ſelf, that is, the Happineſs and Bleſſedneſs of the enjoyment of God, and the Love of him, and Likeneſs to him. If this Soul be then in a perpetual Torment, and for ever, How can it enjoy any thing?</p>
            <p>As we may ſee perſons, that have all the things of this World about them, if they have a Spirit ſunk into Trouble, Diſquiet, Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or, Melancholly, which is a loſt ſtate in this World; a Poor Man that hath not the Thouſandth part of what ſuch a one hath, ſhall yet enjoy much more than he: Such a one, ſaith <hi>Solomon, Eats in darkneſs,</hi> as it were in a Dungeon. How much more when a Spirit comes into its own proper ſtate, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ind nothing within, nor without it ſelf ſuitable to it, but all
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48863:6"/> contrary to its Life and Peace; For it is granted to Souls here to be in a ſtate of Probation, and Tryal, under the Grace of the Mediator, and to ſome ſuch degrees of enjoyment of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God, that they do not feel, at leaſt to ſuch extremity the loſs of themſelves, and the Horror of that ſtate of being loſt, although they are dayly loſing their Souls in what of this World they enjoy; This is generally, and even almoſt univerſally vouchſafed, becauſe God looks upon Mankind through that object of Love, that Son of His Love, to ſee whether they will return to him on the Principles of his Grace; he endures therefore with Patience, and much Long ſuffering the Veſſels of Wrath fitted to Deſtruction, or while they fit themſelves to it: And this, and the Dealings of God with ſuch, is one of the great Myſteries of his Providence and Government of the World by the Mediator.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Soul</hi> often in Scripture Language, ſignifies the whole Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as in the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles,</hi> beſides the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> The number of them that believed were ſo many Souls, or Perſons, that is, Spirits in Bodies; and ſo certainly Chriſt here means: In a parallel Scripture therefore, <hi>Luke</hi> 9. 25. It is ſaid, <hi>What is a Man profited, if he Gain the whole World,</hi> and <hi>loſe himſelf,</hi> or <hi>be caſt away;</hi> Our Lord is here ſpeaking of a Man, as I intimated, under the reſemblance of a Merchant, adventuring himſelf by Sea in the purſuit after Riches: Now ſaith Chriſt, If ſuch a one <hi>Gain the whole World</hi> by the Adventure, and loſe himſelf, What has that Man got by all his undertaking; So if a Man <hi>loſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi> in that Great State of the Reſurrection; of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> at the Glory that is to come; If he ſhall be then in a pity<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, forlorn, deſpiſed ſtate, an undone, ſorrowful Being, a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Removed from all enjoyment, and that he knows, and finds himſelf ſo; <hi>What will it profit</hi> ſuch a one, to have <hi>gained the whole World,</hi> and to be in that loſt State?</p>
            <p>And that our Lord intended this very ſtate of the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and of every Man's ſelf in that ſtate, is plain by his going on, and declaring the <hi>Son of Man's coming</hi> in the <hi>Glory of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> with the <hi>Holy Angels,</hi> and <hi>Rewarding every Man according to his works;</hi> and then ſhall every one know, and feel the loſs of himſelf, who has thus <hi>Loſt</hi> himſelf. So <hi>Souls,</hi> is us'd for <hi>Perſons</hi> in the <hi>Firſt Reſurrection,</hi> Rev. 29. 4.</p>
            <p>2. By all that hath been ſpoken, it appears what the <hi>Loſs of a Soul</hi> is; It is a loſs from Holineſs, Happineſs, and Bleſſedneſs:
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48863:7"/> which <hi>Loſs,</hi> the <hi>Gain of the whole World</hi> can never Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe.</p>
            <p>3. An <hi>Exchange</hi> for a <hi>Loſt Soul,</hi> is ſome way or means of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering a <hi>loſt Soul</hi> into a ſtate of Holineſs and Happineſs, in the enjoyment of God, Likeneſs and Conformity to Him: And this it is the <hi>loſt Soul</hi> will ſo earneſtly cry out for, and that cannot be found.</p>
            <p>The Propoſition I lay down is this: The <hi>Loſs</hi> of a <hi>Man's Soul,</hi> is a <hi>Loſs</hi> ſo exceeding great, and the <hi>Exchange</hi> of Redemption, or for the Recovery of it, if once <hi>loſt,</hi> ſo impoſſible to be found, That when all this comes (as it ſhall certainly be) to be clearly underſtood, and deeply Reſented; It will fully appear, To have <hi>Gain'd the whole World,</hi> much leſs any part of it, at ſuch a Rate, as the <hi>Loſs of the Soul,</hi> cannot yield the leaſt allay to the Bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ariſing from ſuch a Loſs, but will exceedingly increaſe it; For a Man ſhall come to thoſe loud Complaints and Ejulations, thoſe <hi>weepings, wailings,</hi> and <hi>gnaſhings af Teeth;</hi> when he finds he hath loſt that into Miſery, that hath all the Feeling, Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Good, or Evil, Happineſs, or Miſery; the whole power of Enjoyment or Reſentment within it ſelf; That he hath loſt himſelf, his whole ſelf, or perſon, Then will he cry out, Oh! who will give me a Ranſome for my <hi>Soul?</hi> for my <hi>Self?</hi> where ſhall I have it? He goes up to Heaven, down to Hell, he ſearches the whole Creation to find it; Where ſhall I find, ſaith he, what will be taken in <hi>Exchange</hi> for a <hi>loſt, undone Soul?</hi> For who can make his Bed in the Torments of a <hi>Wounded Spirit,</hi> ſcorching worſe than Flames? Who can dwell with the <hi>Devour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Fire,</hi> the <hi>Conſuming Anger of the Living God?</hi> or with the <hi>Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Burnings</hi> of an <hi>Enraged Conſcience?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To make out this in full Diſcourſe, and Argument, I propoſe Three Heads:</p>
            <p n="1">1. To ſhew, That if a Man could dye with the <hi>whole World</hi> in his Hand, he would be a <hi>Loſt</hi> Man on this Account, That the World could be no proviſion for him, or the leaſt ſuitable in that True and Everlaſting Self; his <hi>Soul,</hi> as in the ſtate of <hi>Separated Spirits;</hi> or <hi>Himſelf,</hi> in the ſtate of the <hi>Reſurrection;</hi> and ſo he muſt be <hi>Loſt</hi> on that Account.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That this <hi>Loſt State</hi> cannot be ſlumbered away in ſilence, but he muſt, and ſhall come to thoſe vehement ſearches, after ſome <hi>Exchange</hi> for a <hi>Loſt Soul,</hi> and <hi>Self;</hi> and there being none to be
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48863:7"/> found, thoſe ſearches muſt needs turn into Rage and Fury upon their ſo dreadful diſappointment.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I ſhall therefore enquire into the way of loſing a Soul ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our Lords preſent ſcope, and drift of Diſcourſe: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if we cloſely attend, we ſhall find it out of the Road of our Common Thoughts.</p>
            <p>And unto all theſe, I will ſubjoyn the moſt preſſing Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that ſo naturally flow from thoſe Heads, fully open'd, and enlarg'd upon:</p>
            <p>I begin with the Firſt; The True, Real, Solid Senſe and Reaſon of Things, that none of us can deny; That a Soul muſt needs be loſt that hath no Proviſion, but the <hi>World,</hi> though it were the <hi>whole World;</hi> that is; If ſuch a Thing could indeed be: And though I muſt humbly acknowledg, <hi>I am no way ſufficient for theſe Things,</hi> or the mighty conſiderations pertaining to this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; yet they themſelves are ſo great, that if they be extracted out of all Diſcourſe, and be but felt in, and by themſelves, they muſt needs prevail in our Thoughts; the Holy Spirit thereunto <hi>working in us mightily.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. There is no Compariſon between a Man's <hi>Soul,</hi> a Man's <hi>Self</hi> in the Heighth, and Depth, the Breadth and Length of his <hi>True Being,</hi> his <hi>True Self,</hi> and the World, though it were the <hi>whole World;</hi> A Being Apprehenſive of God, capable of enjoying Him, capable of Eternal Things, of <hi>Righteouſneſs, Peace,</hi> and <hi>Joy in the Holy Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For what Compare can there be between a Being prepared with Sentiments, and Capacities for theſe Things, and the narrow and pent up notions and dimenſions of our ſelves, as Creatures, that eat ſuch Meat, and drink ſuch Drinks, that wear ſuch Cloaths, and dwell in ſuch Houſes, or Appartments, have ſuch an Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page and Retinue? So widely different is the proportion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the World, and an Immortal Spirit, an Immortal ſelf: For the World is ſuited only to thoſe low Notions and Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of a Man's Self, and it can extend no further: So that the Spirit, and True Self of a Man even now, in this State, in this Body finds a want in the greateſt abundance of theſe, Things, and cries out upon them all, <hi>Vanity and vexation of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit;</hi> and though it be buddled up, and muffled, and kept quiet by all Arts imaginable, yet it complains, and inwardly mourns to it ſelf; becauſe it hath not the true ſatisfaction, and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; the <hi>Fibres</hi> (as I may ſo ſpeak) of the <hi>Spiritual Stomach</hi> and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48863:8"/> 
               <hi>Appetite,</hi> are ſo often twitched with the hunger of ſomething more Excellent and Divine; I mean, Thoſe deep and inward Sentiments, We are made for higher enjoyments than of this World, often ſtir and move do what we can to the contrary. And if it be thus now, much more will this be in that future ſtate, when a <hi>Soul</hi> will be fully explicated, unfolded, let our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to its utmoſt Capacities; Then will all the World plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be no other than the fitting the Coat of an Infant to a Giant; Oh! how much too wide, and too large is that true Self for all theſe, too extenſive to be ſo provided for! To tell an Immortal Spirit, or a Man riſen from the Dead, of Meat, and Drink, and ſumptuous Cloathing, of Houſes, Eſtates, and Money; you ſpeak, I may ſay, Infinitely below the Dignity, and Majeſty of ſuch a Being: It will ſay to the World, <hi>All theſe thy things periſh with thee;</hi> That thou couldſt think I could be provided for by them, or that Eternal Things could be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed with them!</p>
            <p>Oh, that therefore now, we could ſay to our ſelves, Can I think of God, of Chriſt, of his Spirit, of Eternal Happineſs, or Miſery? Have I Thoughts that can embrace ſuch Things as theſe! Am I great enough for ſuch Thoughts? Can I think of enjoying God, and Living in the pureſt entercourſes of Reaſon, and Holieſt Underſtanding? Can there be an enterview between my Spirit and the <hi>Father of Spirits,</hi> God in Chriſt? and do you talk to me of ſuch poor and low things as are firſt moſt proper to Beaſts, and Creatures of Senſe only? the food of Brutes; the meat of Worms; and to me only in that low ſtate and part wherein I am allied to them.</p>
            <p>I know how very hard it is for us in this low Carnal ſtate, to take in the Reaſon of this, as it were vain to entertain Beaſts with the Diſcourſes of <hi>Mathematicks,</hi> of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> or of <hi>Virtue;</hi> And hereby the <hi>Children of Men may know themſelves to be but Beaſts,</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks; a higher kind of Beaſts: And it were well for them, if their <hi>Spirits,</hi> who have thus converſed in Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, might be ſuffered to <hi>go downward,</hi> as <hi>Beaſts;</hi> ſo indeed, ſuch Men would have them do when they come to dye: But this cannot be, as God ſaid to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> They would fain have been as the <hi>Heathen Families,</hi> but He would <hi>Bring them under the Bond of the Covenant</hi> of <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> of thoſe He called his People; ſo ſuch would fain be as the Beaſts; But this ſhall not be, God will bring them under the Law of Spiritual and Everlaſting Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and of the Family of never dying Spirits.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:48863:8"/>
            <p>Let us but a little Appeal to our own Minds, and put them a while into their own Action, into their own proper Exerciſe; and we ſhall find in their Enquiries after God, after Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, after the enjoyment of him in the Blood, and Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of Jeſus Chriſt, and the operations of his Spirit; That they are made for theſe Things: And how poor then will all the things in this World appear to be, when we come to the height of this Action and Activity.</p>
            <p>And though we take ſo much pleaſure and delight in theſe now, yet ſeeing we can riſe up to higher things, and frame no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of them, it is certain we are made for thoſe higher things, and they muſt be our ſtate for ever; For it is certain, this is a great Rule and Maxime, By the moſt excellent part in every Thing, is its proper and laſting Good, to be known and judged of. It is therefore our Degeneracy, and Depravedneſs, or to ſpeak the moſt Favourably and Charitably, It is our <hi>Childiſhneſs,</hi> and <hi>Imperfection,</hi> that we are ſo pleaſed; and that we have not Higher, Greater, Larger, more Conſtant Thoughts in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Things; as the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>When I was a Child, I thought as a Child, I ſpake as a Child, I did as a Child; but when I became a Man, I put away Childiſh things from me.</hi> Men look upon the things of their Childhood with great diſdain, and ſo put them away from them, as nothing to them; when they come to be Men they change both their overvalue of Trifles, and their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervalue of Weightier things, they then had; This indeed, the Apoſtle ſpeaks of our Higheſt Attainments in Grace here; and it is hardly allowable to apply it to the Caſe we are upon; but in a charitable Condeſention to our weakneſs, it may be alluded to: But it is moſt certain, when we come to know what the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of God is, what it is to <hi>drink of the River of his pleaſures;</hi> when he <hi>ſhews us the Path of Life, when we come to his Preſence,</hi> where is <hi>fulneſs of Joy,</hi> and to the <hi>Pleaſures of his Right Hand, that are for evermore;</hi> What Trifles will all theſe things appear to us! And on the other ſide, even the ſorrows of a loſt ſtate, will make us ſee what empty Vanities they all were: On both ſides then, Oh, with what a deſpiſal ſhall we look upon the things we are ſo fond of now, that we have been ſo endear'd to here! Thoſe things, that if we cannot have them, we, as <hi>Amnon,</hi> are ready to <hi>die for,</hi> we ſhall then with Scorn and Hatred, put out, and ſhut the door upon. If we could really think, with what an Eye Angels and Saints look upon thoſe things we make ſuch a do with, that take up our time, and we call Great Buſineſs;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48863:9"/> How do we ſay ſuch a Time, we muſt take care of ſuch an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament for the Body, ſuch a Proviſion for our Table, ſuch Conveniencies, and Furniture for our Houſes, ſuch a concern of Trade, ſuch a ſettlement of our Revenue! and theſe are things that paſs for great things, as we think them now, eſpecially Trade, Eſtate, or ſuch like; For even ſome of theſe, wiſe Men count Trifles now, and deſpiſe thoſe who are taken up about them; But even the higheſt, the weightieſt of them, when we come to underſtand them in another World, we ſhall wonder how we could lay out ſo many thoughts upon them, in the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of things ſo much greater, that concern our much more worthy Selves, in our Spirits, in our Immortal State: With what admirable Divine Eloquence therefore <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays, <hi>Happy is the Man that findeth wiſdom, and the Man that getteth underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; For the Merchandiſe of it is better than the Merchandiſe of Silver, and the gain thereof, than of fine Gold: She is more precious than Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies, and all the things thou canſt deſire are not to be compared to her; Length of days in her Right Hand, and in her Left Hand, Riches and Honour; Her ways are ways of pleaſantneſs, and all her paths are peace; She is a Tree of Life to them that lay hold upon Her; and Happy is every one that retaineth her,</hi> Prov. 3. 13, 14, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Here now is the Proviſion proper to Immortal Spirits, to the ſtate of the <hi>Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the dead,</hi> and if we have Wiſdom in degree, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations to that Great State now, theſe things will be our Choice.</p>
            <p>There is a ſolemn Inquiry, <hi>Job</hi> 28. 12. <hi>Where ſhall wiſdom be found, and where is the place of underſtanding? Man knoweth not the price thereof; neither is it found in the Land of the Living; The Depth ſaith, It is not in me; and the Sea ſaith, It is not in me;</hi> that is, it does not Riſe from the Riches of the Earth, nor from the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the Sea: <hi>It cannot be gotten for Gold, neither ſhall Silver be weighed for the price of it; It cannot be valued with the Gold of Ophir; with the precious Onyx, nor the Saphire ſtone; The Gold and the Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtal cannot equal it, and the exchange of it ſhall not be for Jewels of ſine Gold. No mention ſhall be made of the Coral, or of the Pearl, For the price of Wiſdom is above Rubies</hi> Thus the Spirit of God is pleaſed to go on like an Orator, and to ſhew us, that the <hi>whole World</hi> is not worth one <hi>Soul;</hi> and therefore it is not worth <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> that <hi>Wiſdom to Salvation of Souls;</hi> and without which <hi>Souls</hi> are <hi>loſt,</hi> For <hi>He that ſinneth againſt Wiſdom, wrongeth his own Soul; All they that Hate it, Love death.</hi> Thus the <hi>whole World</hi> is Inventoried, as it were; Its chief Riches are <hi>weighed,</hi> and found too <hi>Light</hi> for <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:48863:9"/> In the ſame manner, there is a ſad Reflection on the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery of <hi>Loſt Souls,</hi> For <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Deſtruction ſay, we have Heard the Fame thereof with our Ears;</hi> a moſt lively, and elegant expreſſion of the ſtate of <hi>Loſt Souls;</hi> who in two regards may be ſaid to have <hi>Heard,</hi> or to <hi>Hear</hi> the <hi>Fame thereof with their Ears.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. They that are Loſt, and in a ſtate of Death and Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, had, while in this Life, <hi>Heard the Fame of Wiſdom with their Ears,</hi> in thoſe Diſcourſes of the Goſpel, in that <hi>Law writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten</hi> in our <hi>Hearts</hi> in many motions of Conſcience, <hi>&amp;c. but deſpiſed all its Counſel, and would have none of its Reproof;</hi> ſo they only <hi>Heard</hi> the <hi>Fame,</hi> but never Received, or Entertained Acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with it; It was never as their <hi>Siſter,</hi> or <hi>Kinſwoman,</hi> as <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſpeaks, in intimacy with them: Chriſt is ſaid, in this very ſenſe, to have <hi>Preach'd</hi> of old to the <hi>Spirits, loſt Spirits,</hi> now in <hi>Priſon:</hi> So <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Deſtruction have Heard the Fame of it with their Fars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Fame</hi> of it comes near to them; They <hi>Hear it with their Ears,</hi> but cannot come at it; as <hi>Dives</hi> in <hi>Hell,</hi> Hearing the <hi>Fame</hi> of the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> of <hi>Repentance to Salvation,</hi> deſir'd his <hi>Brothers</hi> might take that Benefit of it, which he had loſt, and could make no purchaſe of, no <hi>Exchange</hi> for it, out of all that World he had had. <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Deſtruction</hi> can find no <hi>Exchange for a Soul,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have nothing to give in <hi>Exchange</hi> for <hi>Wiſdom:</hi> Thus this Expreſſion is parallel to our Saviour's, <hi>What ſhall a Man give in exchange for his Soul?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus now, 'Tis evident, The World, and all the things of it, are no more Commenſurate to the Greatneſs of a <hi>Soul,</hi> or of an Everlaſting <hi>Self,</hi> in all its Offertures than as if Man ſhould ſay He would make a Garment for the Sun; though never ſo Rich and Beautiful a Garment, you know it could bear no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to the Beauty and Excellency of Light, or to the vaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Orb of the Sun: No more can all the Riches, Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, goodly Houſes, or Divertiſements of the World extend to a Soul, or to a Man conſidered in his future State. The very Quality and Dignity of a Being made to be for ever, does ſo beyond all Expreſſion, and Compariſon exceed the Quality, and Intrinſic value of the World.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:48863:10"/>
            <p>So that a man loſes himſelf, and his Soul, while he lays out his thoughts, love, deſire, and expends his Soul upon them; becauſe they are only for the Soul to ſerve it ſelf in ſome ſmall meaſure upon, for its higher end now; but if it center upon them, it is loſt; for they are not worth that in any degree.</p>
            <p>2. If after this enjoyment of the World then (ſuppoſe the longeſt time that can in any Reaſon, Example or Precedent be ſuppoſed) there comes on the eternal duration of an Immortal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, a ſelf in an everlaſting ſtate; A man cannot be profited, <hi>that enjoys the whole world, and loſes his Soul.</hi> For if a Soul be immortal, and for ever, then the State of that Soul and Spirit muſt be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal and for ever alſo; And then if the World be all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion that is made for it, it cannot but be Loſt upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, becauſe the World can be a portion for it only in this Life. Whether therefore a man loſe his Soul by his bad ways of gaining the World; or whether he loſe his Soul by having made no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for it, but only the World, there can be no profit to a man, but extreme loſs by <hi>gaining the World,</hi> becauſe he loſes his Soul for it: For if this Soul be loſt notwithſtanding all the World can do to help it, it is all one to the man whether he have the World, or have it not: For a Soul loſt, is for ever loſt, or elſe it is not <hi>loſt</hi> at all, and if the World cannot redeem that loſs, what is a man the better for the World? it is ſtill the ſame thing: Or if the <hi>Soul</hi> be <hi>lost</hi> by having no proviſion for it but the World, and the World cannot go into Eternity with it, and that ſo it being loſt and miſerable, <hi>What can it profit a man to have gain'd the whole world, and loſe his ſoul?</hi> The World leaves him in the time of his greateſt extremity. Oh how then will our Immortal Spirit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach us, or it ſelf? For man by his Soul or Spirit hath ſuch a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of ſelf reflection, of ſelf charge and condemnation; and in this ſtate it will exerciſe it to the height: It will ſay; What do you make Proviſion for me, for a moment, for a minute, in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon; for a ſpan long, for a hand breadth of time, when I muſt endure Ages of Ages? is this the love you have for an Immortal Spirit, to make ſuch proviſion for it, that is, to endure and laſt a Line parallel to Eternity it ſelf<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and you have provided for it, comparatively, as but for an hour, a day, a minute? would not a Child ſay to a Parent that ſhould make proviſion for it but for a day, a month, a year, that we may ſuppoſe in a courſe of nature, and common providence, may live many years; Is this the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48863:10"/> love you have for me, to make proviſion but for ſo ſhort a time?</p>
            <p>Oh with how much greater reaſon, force and ſting will our Souls ſay to us! How is it that when you underſtood I am prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for Everlaſting, you have only laid up for me for the ſhort time of this Life? <hi>For whoſe ſhall thoſe things be,</hi> you have provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded? you know they cannot be mine, I cannot carry them with me; or if I had all the World, it could do me no good, it could not redeem my loſs in this Eternal State, I muſt go out naked not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding them. Oh let us therefore always remember the Words Scripture ſounds ſo often in our ears; <hi>Everlaſting, Eternal, for ever, always to come;</hi> as <hi>Matt.</hi> 25. 24, <hi>&amp;c. Come ye bleſſed of my Father, inherit the Kingdom prepared for you, &amp;c.</hi> And on the other ſide; <hi>Depart from me, ye curſed, into everlaſting Fire, prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the Devil and his Angels:</hi> And <hi>theſe go away into everlaſting puniſhment,</hi> and the <hi>righteous into life eternal.</hi> Oh that every one of us, both ſpeaking and hearing could deeply conſider this; I am to be for ever, and therefore what do you ſpeak to me of things that are to be only for a ſhort time?</p>
            <p>And if it be for poſterity, that we are urged; even that is but a Notion of this World, and of this Life; though it look big, and ſound great, and carry a fair and honourable pretention, and <hi>men</hi> upon it <hi>call their Lands after their own Names,</hi> and their <hi>Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity indeed approve their Sayings.</hi> All this, notwithſtanding the Spirit of God ſays; <hi>This their way is their folly.</hi> And when men come into an Eternal Condition, this Bubble falls; there are no ſuch Notions there; <hi>For,</hi> ſays <hi>Job, their S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns come to honour, and they know it not;</hi> and <hi>they are brought low, and they perceive it not of them;</hi> But their <hi>Fleſh upon them has pain,</hi> and <hi>their ſouls within them mourn:</hi> That is, A man has not the leaſt abatement of the black and mournful ſtate of a loſt Soul by it. We ſhould therefore ſay; Shall I be miſerable for ever, that I may leave an Eſtate to my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily? Shall I be miſerable to Eternity? Thus I may entail upon my Poſterity, what I ſhall in my own Eternal ſelf have no more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation too, than a Stranger, and yet be in miſery for ſo forecaſting for my Poſterity:</p>
            <p>It is certain the Tongues of Angels and men is not enough to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs this thing according to the weight of it. Indeed Words are nothing alone, but as they are ſubordinate to the Divine Spirit preſſing the things themſelves; For things preſs cloſe, and make a ſtrong impreſſion upon the heart, Mind, and Affections, when ſo ſet home.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:48863:11"/>
            <p>Oh therefore that I might be the Miniſter of God, to utter Things to you, and that he would enable you to take things to your ſelves out of all Expreſſions and Words; that in all this caſe we may not be prevail'd upon by vain Fantaſies and appearances from this World, and the Scheme or Guiſe of it, and find no weight, force nor Authority in things ſo ſolid and real. For whether we will hear, or forbear, it is certain this carries the greateſt Reaſon; That we ſhould not incur an Eternal Loſs for a momentary and preſent Intereſt. This is according to all the Reaſon in the World.</p>
            <p>3. From hence it follows, that all appearances in this World, and in the out-ſide happineſs and proſperity of it, any further than it is ſubordinated to the ſupreme ends of the glory of God, and of our Eternal Salvation, is happineſs, welfare, proſperity, enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment only in a diſguiſe, in Maſquerade, or as on a Stage.</p>
            <p>Now if an Actor on a Stage ſhould forget what he really is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he acts the part of a King, or any great Perſonage, becauſe he is under ſuch an Appearance and Character in a Play, and think himſelf to be ſuch a one, how great would the Deluſion and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toxication be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> And ſuch is the Faſcination, and as I may juſtly call it, the Fanaticiſm, and Enthuſiaſm the buſineſs and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment, and enrichments of this World tranſport men into: They make them forget what a little and ſhort intereſt men have in this World; how far from an indefeiſable ſtate of Inheritance as they love to ſpeak, a Term, not ſo much as for Life, That is, a Proviſion ſo long as we are to be, and to live: For this (as we have ſeen) is to Eternity, not ſo much as a Term for years, which is a time certain; whereas <hi>This night our ſouls may be required of us;</hi> and then <hi>whole ſhall thoſe things be,</hi> we <hi>have provided?</hi> All therefore we do or ſpeak, or magnifie our ſelves in though upon any thing in this World, is but ſo much Theatre, Farce and Maſquerade, as to all that ariſes from this World.</p>
            <p>And thus much we might learn from the Stage: Herein we are more fooliſh than thoſe Actors, however their Profeſſion is juſtly more deſpicable than of the pooreſt Mechanick, or Day-la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourer; that they do not think themſelves to be what they act, but know their true State and Character, and uſe thoſe Theatrical Garments and Repreſentations for a real ſupport of themſelves and their Families, and conſider in the midſt of all thoſe feigned Appearances, their true Neceſſities at home. Even thus, as Chriſt inſtructs us, ſhould we <hi>make to our ſelves Friends of the mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:48863:11"/> of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs,</hi> make improvement of all we ſeem to be heer, that when we <hi>fail</hi> from all theſe, <hi>we may be received to Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Habitations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But alas, how generally do we value our ſelves by our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitting our ſelves, as upon a Theatre; we give our ſelves a ſecret Applauſe, as we are Men of Mode, as we have behaved our ſelves in our Buſineſs, Trade, Appearance in Courts of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature, in the Courts of Princes, in ſuch or ſuch Company; and <hi>Men will praiſe us, when we do,</hi> as they think, <hi>well for our ſelves</hi> in theſe things, becauſe they are like unto us: We think our ſelves, what we are in Acting, and forget that true Self at home, that, though it be indeed the Noble and Princely part, the Laſting and Eternal part, the only True and Real Self, yet is put under the diſguiſe of a Slave; But, oh! how amazed ſhall we be, when that Self ſtarts out, and appears like it ſelf; and we have loſt it for a Thing, a Life, a Being, a Happineſs, ſo only in a Vizor! Oh! How will this Amaze and Torment us for ever! when in vain we ſhall cry out, I never knew, nor thought my ſelf to be ſuch a one, as I now find my ſelf; and as Chriſt ſays; So is <hi>He that lays up Treaſure for Himſelf,</hi> under ſo falſe a Maſque of ſelf, and is not <hi>Rich towards God,</hi> and his True Self; ſo ſhall we find it: Such Fools, ſuch <hi>Enthuſiaſts,</hi> heated with vain and wordly Imagination ſhall we be found. And yet dayly are ſeen ſuch <hi>Servants on Horſeback,</hi> falſe Selves ſet aloft; and <hi>Princes,</hi> the True Self, the Immortal Soul made to <hi>walk on Foot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus the Spirit of God, ſetting out the State of wicked Men in the World, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. He ſets it out, as in this Maſquerade, till the Diſguize and Vizor be pulled off; <hi>There are no Bands in their Death,</hi> but their <hi>Strength is firm.</hi> They dye oftentimes (as they ſay) in the Bed of Honour, with all Advantages about them without fear of what's to come: <hi>They are not in Trouble as other Men, neither are they Plagued as other Men;</hi> Therefore <hi>Pride compaſſeth them about as a Chain</hi> (He means) of Gold. They take ſtate upon them, as great Princes, or Magiſtrates, with their Rich Collars, their Chains of Gold; <hi>Violence covereth them as a Garment,</hi> They take Power, and Command to themſelves, to enforce their pleaſure; <hi>Their Eyes ſtand out with fatneſs,</hi> They car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Great Port, and Preſence, as we ſpeak; <hi>They have more, than
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:48863:12"/> heart could wiſh;</hi> They are <hi>Corrupt, and ſpeak wickedly; Concerning Oppreſſion they ſpeak loftily,</hi> Who dares undertake them? Who can attack them, or <hi>make War with them?</hi> They ſpeak Great and Big, as if Heaven and Earth was their own; <hi>They ſet their Mouth againſt the Heaven, and their Tongue walks through the Earth.</hi> Theſe are the <hi>ungodly proſpering in their way.</hi> This looks very great for a Time; but it is all but as on a Stage; It is all Stage-Play, However, Good Men are ready to be troubled at it, as if it were real; <hi>But I did but go,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt, to the Houſe of God, then underſtood I their end;</hi> I ſaw the end of the Play, and it ends as we ſay in a Tragedy; All Horror at the laſt; <hi>Surely thou didſt ſet them in ſlippery places; Thou caſtedſt them down to deſtruction; How are they brought into deſolation in a moment? They are utterly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed with Terrors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am fully aſſured, All the Wit of Man could never have reached this height; no Poetry, no O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y; only the Spirit of God, who perfectly knows, and ſpeaks Things, Things ſo great as to find themſelves ſuch loughty and maſſy Words, when underſtood, as the Divine Spirit underſtands them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How are they brought into deſolation as in a moment! They are utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſumed with Terrors;</hi> As ſoon as they are got but never ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle on that ſide the Line, beyond this World, They are All in <hi>Deſolation</hi> and <hi>Terror. As a Dream when one awaketh; ſo, Oh Lord, when thou awakeſt, thou ſhalt deſpiſe their Image.</hi> All their State here is but <hi>Dream</hi> and <hi>Image,</hi> meer Stage Appearance, Maſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rade and Diſguiſe.</p>
            <p>To bring all this home then to what we ſhould be and do, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſame <hi>Pſalmiſt;</hi> We ſhould acknowledg our <hi>Brutiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>Folly,</hi> in being at all concerned with ſuch Spectres of Happineſs, loſing in the mean time their Precious Immortal Selves: We ſhould reſign our ſelves wholly to Divine Conduct, <hi>To be led by his Counſel, till we are brought to his Glory;</hi> We ſhould look wholly to and for him, <hi>Whom have I in Heaven but thee? and there is none on Earth I deſire beſide thee;</hi> &amp;c. All <hi>fails,</hi> even a whole World; All, except God alone; <hi>All far from him periſh: It is good</hi> then for <hi>us to draw near to him,</hi> that we may declare the <hi>wonders</hi> of his <hi>Power</hi> in his <hi>Grace</hi> to us, <hi>ſetting us before his Face for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:48863:12"/>
            <p>I come to the ſecond Head, to ſhew you, in what way accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our Saviours Diſcourſe, and the ſcope of it, we come to loſe a Soul; For this is a very <hi>critical</hi> Point, and that, if cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly applied, would try us, as by a <hi>Jealouſy Water,</hi> whether we are Chriſt's or not? I ſhall endeavour to be very brief in it, though the Things themſelves require vaſt, and largeſt Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
            <p>Now therefore I muſt tell you, that we, even <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> are under the name of Chriſtians and Proteſtants, a very Dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate Race. We end, where Chriſtianity in its own True, Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine, and Tranſcendent Powers begins. For Chriſtianity ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther finds Men Sober, and, as we ſpeak, of Good Lives, as the <hi>young Man</hi> in the Goſpel, that was <hi>Lovely</hi> in the Eyes of Chriſt for all Moral Accompliſhments, <hi>Matt.</hi> 9. compar'd with <hi>Mark</hi> 17. or it preſently makes them ſo, as <hi>Zaccheus</hi> and other Converts, and then it plants them with its nobler Principles, and Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: It takes for granted, no groſs Impieties, or Immoralities ſhould be amongſt them, not ſo much (as the Apoſtle ſays) as <hi>once named</hi> among them, as <hi>Becometh Saints;</hi> but then it hath much higher G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aces, Powers and Actions to Communicate to them; whereas among us, If a Man be no Swearer, Profeſſed Prophane Perſon, no fordidly Covetous Perſon, Defrauder, or Oppreſſor, Talks, and Lives Soberly, and Joyns in the Duties of Publick Worſhip, and Acknowledgment of God, we are ready to ſay, This is an Excellent Man: But this was not ſo in the Eye of Chriſt; For He in his manner of Diſcourſe, and Preaching <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> to the Sober and Moral Men, and our Men of Good Lives <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Religious Men, and that diſtinguiſh themſelves from the Lewd and Irreligious: Now ſaith Chriſt to ſuch, whom we are ready to think very very ſafe, Take heed you are not the Perſons <hi>loſing your Souls;</hi> though you do it with a great deal of Gravity, Soberneſs, and Becommingneſs in the W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rld; and under ſuch a profeſſion of Chriſtianity and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, that no one ſhould ſo much as dare to queſtion your Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, Leſt He offend and ſcandalize you, and diſcourage All from being Chriſtians; as the <hi>young Man,</hi> who went away ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful, diſcouraged, and as we ſpeak, diſoblige<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>ked off from the Doctrine of Chriſt; and ſtaggering the very Diſciples, who cried out, <hi>Who then can be ſaved!</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:48863:13"/>
            <p>I will therefore lead you into the occaſion of theſe words of our Lor'ds; <hi>What is a Man profited, if he gain the whole World, and loſe his Soul,</hi> &amp;c? In this <hi>Chapter, v.</hi> 21. Began Jeſus to ſhew to his Diſciples, that he muſt go up unto <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that Head City, <hi>and Seat of the Jewiſh Religion,</hi> and the Doctors of it, the <hi>Elders, Chief Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Scribes</hi> that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld the Standard of it; of whom He <hi>muſt ſuffer many Things,</hi> and <hi>be killed,</hi> and <hi>Raiſed again the Third Day;</hi> I muſt (ſaith he) be Mocked, I muſt be Buffeted, I muſt be Spit upon, I muſt be Laughed at, and Drol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon; and I muſt dye that ignominious death of a Slave, of a great Criminal, and Malefactor; But I ſhall <hi>Riſe again the Third Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now <hi>Peter</hi> looking not at all upon the <hi>Riſing the Third Day,</hi> but letting that paſs for a Phantaſy, a Thing in the Clouds, as we do All Diſcourſe of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> at this Time; elſe that might have Reconciled him: But He, altogether intent upon the Suffering part, began to take Chriſt to task, and to <hi>Rebuke him,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Be it far from thee, Lord; This ſhall not be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee,</hi> Let not this thing be once thought of, That ſuch a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon as Thou art ſhould be thus Treated, <hi>Deal more mercifully with thy ſelf;</hi> For Thou who canſt do all things, canſt hinder it if thou pleaſeſt: But <hi>Chriſt turned to Peter,</hi> and with an unuſual ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity ſaid to him, <hi>Get thee behind me Satan; For Thou ſavoureſt not the Things that be of God, but thoſe that be of Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then he adds, This is a Thing, I am ſo far from being turn'd off from, that I eſtabliſh it, as a Rule for All my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples; <hi>If any Man will come after me,</hi> as my Diſciple, <hi>Let him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny himſelf, take up his Croſs, and follow me,</hi> in all this I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented upon my ſelf. And if any Man think much of this, and chuſes rather <hi>to ſave his Life,</hi> ſuch a one <hi>ſhall loſe it;</hi> but He that <hi>loſes his Life</hi> thus <hi>for my ſake,</hi> ſhall <hi>find it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this is, as if Chriſt ſhould ſay, I do not only ſay, you muſt leave your Debaucheries, the Groſs Pride, and Vanities of this World; but you muſt come to that to be willing to loſe your Lives, you muſt <hi>Take up your Croſs,</hi> do that, the Nature of Man ſo much abhors.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:48863:13"/>
            <p>Now, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> having ſuch a Love to Chriſt, ſaid, <hi>Let it be far from thee,</hi> ſo we are ready to ſay too, looking upon our ſelves, or any other, a Man of Condition, a Man of Quality, as we ſpeak; what, you come to <hi>Take up your Croſs,</hi> to <hi>deny your ſelf,</hi> to go lower in the World! This ſhall not be. But Chriſt is poſitive; If any Man, when required by me, to <hi>loſe his Life, will ſave it,</hi> He ſhall loſe it; But if any will <hi>loſe his Life,</hi> ſo required by me; He ſhall <hi>find it</hi> in a higher Life, as I ſhall find my Life the <hi>Third Day.</hi> Now, ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Soul,</hi> are, you know, the Power and Meaſure of all enjoyment; and if you <hi>loſe</hi> your True <hi>Life, Soul, Self,</hi> though you <hi>gain the whole World,</hi> what do you get by it? But beyond this, If you come to Repent ſo great a Loſs, and to cry out, <hi>What ſhall I give</hi> as an <hi>Exchange,</hi> a Ranſom for that Soul, that Life loſt, and no ſuch can be found? How Miſerable will you be! Here is the very Reaſon, and Thread of our Lord's Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>And herewith agree all his Diſcourſes on this ſubject; Let us take them in the Goſpel Verity and Purity, the very words of Chriſt, <hi>Luke.</hi> 14. 35. There were <hi>Great Multitudes following Chriſt;</hi> Many were taken with the Excellency of his Diſcourſe, with the Majeſty of his Holy Converſation, and Miracles; But he turned to them, and ſaith, I would not have you miſtake me, <hi>If any Man come after me, and hate not his Father, and Mother, and Wife, and Children,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and his own Life alſo, He cannot be my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple;</hi> And therefore (ſaith he) Conſider well, and the Point of Conſideration He ſets out by two cloſe ſimilitudes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Chriſtianity undertaken in the Truth of it, is like <hi>Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Tower,</hi> which he that does, had need <hi>ſit down firſt,</hi> and <hi>count the charge;</hi> and it is like beginning a War, in which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual Power is to be well ſtated; leſt otherwiſe All end in ſcorn and Ruine. So ſaith He, Whoever undertakes to be a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> to be my <hi>Diſciple,</hi> muſt firſt conſider, whether he can bear it out.</p>
            <p>I ſay, To be a <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> For Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Diſciple,</hi> and we generally ſay <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> And, indeed, by <hi>Oracle,</hi> as from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the <hi>Diſciples were called Chriſtians,</hi> Acts 11. 26. So to be a <hi>Diſciple,</hi> and to be a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> (however the word, <hi>Diſciple,</hi> be become a word of ſcorn among us) is the ſame thing. Now if any Man will be a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> here are the Terms of it, and we
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:48863:14"/> muſt drop the very Name of Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tian, if we are not thus pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd; And yet who is thus prepar'd?</p>
            <p>Take another Scripture, <hi>John</hi> 12. 2, 4. Chriſt conſidering his own dying, compares the thing to a <hi>caſting a Corn of Wheat into the ground; Verily, verily, ſaith Chriſt, except a Corn</hi> of Wheat fall into the Ground, <hi>it abideth alone; but if it die, it bringeth forth much fruit: He that loveth his life ſhall loſe it; and he that hateth his life in this world ſhall keep it to life eternal.</hi> Here is the plain ſenſe of lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ng Life, or a Soul, when we loſe Life Eternal; and to loſe that with the gain of a Life, that the <hi>whole world can make great,</hi> is a loſs wholly unaccountable, intollerable, and irreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diable, notwithſtanding the moſt paſſionate deſires of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, or remedy, which ſhall ever enflame the loſs.</p>
            <p>Now a <hi>Corn of Wheat,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, to this purpoſe, <hi>except it die, abides alone:</hi> it can never be any more than a Corn of Wheat; and at laſt, as ſuch, it putrifies; but if it be <hi>caſt into the ground,</hi> and die, it riſes in all the flouriſh of Nature.</p>
            <p>So if a man ſay, He'll be this great man, this rich man, this man of Power and Honour, this man of Mode and pleaſure in this World, and adventure for what is to come; ſay what you will, ſaith he, I will not diminiſh from the Figure I am, or can hope or attain to make.</p>
            <p>Why, if ſo, ſaith Chriſt, you may, as you can, be that Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, but you ſhall never be any more; and when you come to die, what becomes of that Figure? And beſides, beyond that, <hi>viz.</hi> when That Figure is to be no more; there ariſes the Loſs of a Soul, and of Life Eternal; which is beyond all expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, a Loſs dreadful, and without any repriſal, or reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very.</p>
            <p>And to this very purpoſe is that ſo known Diſcourſe of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>James;</hi> Thus the Truth of that Faith which juſtifies, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the mighty Operations of it in ſelf-denial, ſelf-reſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and of all our Intereſts in this World, as <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hab</hi> made: Such Acts of Faith, as the Apoſtle gives a Catalogue of, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. by which the Elders obtained ſo great, ſo <hi>good</hi> a <hi>Report;</hi> which if well conſider'd, would much abate the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal part of that Scripture; the Apoſtle being not in diſcourſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:48863:14"/> upon the conſtant Ordinary Works of Moral Obedience, but of thoſe Heroick Acts oppoſing to the Body of Profeſſion that mighty Spirit of <hi>Juſtifying Faith,</hi> giving up all to God and Chriſt.</p>
            <p>I will therefore but name the Particulals, wherein this is to be ſhewn, that we are ready to forſake all to follow Chriſt.</p>
            <p>1. It is certain, the very forſaking of all in the plain Letter, or Matter of Fact, was the Caſe for three hundred years and more, after the Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt; it was ſo diſpos'd by the Supreme Lord of Time, if a man would be Chriſt's Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, if he would take up him to be a Chriſtian at that time, he muſt undervalue for the ſake of Chriſt, the whole World, and all Relations and Intereſts in it, or elſe he could not be ſo: So that this was continually brought to the Beame, to the Scale, whether a man's own Soul, or the whole World weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed moſt?</p>
            <p>Indeed after three hundred years, and ſomething more, the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> made ſome appearance in the Chriſtian Empire, and the Chriſtians came to be in a Condition of Honour and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and outward, proſperity; and the Biſhops, and Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, as they call'd themſelves, became the greateſt of the Earth: But if we believe Eccleſiaſtick Hiſtory, there was a Voice from Heaven at that time; <hi>This day is Poyſon diffus'd into the Church:</hi> But whether that were ſo or not, certainly the thing was moſt true: For hence aroſe an Opinion That Chriſtianity in ſuch a low and impure ſtate, as the World was then in, and hath continued in to this day, did yet advance to worldly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and greatneſs; or that the profeſſion of Chriſt and his Goſpel, made men with no greater Influences of holineſs appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the ſame time, great, and rich, and Lords, then which nothing is more contrary to the Kingdom of Chriſt, and which brought in <hi>Antichriſtianiſm, a mock Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon, and even out of the Chriſtian Empire. But this was the State of what we call Antiquity before the Chriſtian Empire, or the time of the pureſt Chriſtianity; it was a laying down all at the <hi>foot of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:48863:15"/>
            <p>2. It is certain every one of us ought to be prepared, to have a Mind Fixed, and ready to give up All to Chriſt; elſe we cannot be Diſciples of Chriſt; ſuppoſe any of us have Advantages of Deſcent, of Place, of Eſtate, of Credit, of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, of Great Abilities of Underſtanding, of all the Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of Living, Attendance, Equipage, Garb; If we cannot be willing to lay all this aſide, for Chriſts ſake, and to be wrapt up in the vileſt Appearance, we cannot be Chriſts Diſciples, and ſo cannot be Chriſtians, For Diſciples are called Chriſtians by Oracle.</p>
            <p>And as I ſaid before of the <hi>Chriſtian Empire,</hi> until it came in there was nothing but Poverty, Perſecution, Diſgrace, and all the Torments the wits of <hi>Pagans</hi> could invent upon Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; ſo in After Times, when <hi>Antichriſtianiſm</hi> came to a height, there was no enjoying the Purity of Chriſtianity, but the Name of <hi>Hereticks</hi> Entitled all thoſe, who would be Chriſtians, not according, to what they call'd <hi>Holy Church,</hi> but according to the Goſpel it ſelf, to all the Cruelty, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution and Torments, the Heathen had before found out, and Practiſed upon Chriſtians; which now <hi>Antichriſtians</hi> took up againſt ſincere <hi>Chriſtians:</hi> But for this laſt Age, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt another to it, our <hi>Reformation</hi> hath brought in a greater Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the <hi>Protestant Profeſſion,</hi> and the ſame Honour, Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles and Grandieur on <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> But we had need take care we do not abuſe it; For if we are not in the preparation of our Hearts, Dying, as a <hi>Corn of Wheat,</hi> we cannot, in the Senſe of the great Maſter, and Founder of Chriſtianity be his <hi>Diſciples</hi> or <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> And it is much to be conſider'd, All things of Worldly greatneſs, and Enjoyment are ſtill un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this Perjudice, that the <hi>Kingdoms of this World</hi> are yet in <hi>Beaſtian Hands,</hi> of the Laſt of <hi>Daniels Beaſtian Powers,</hi> the Antichriſt the Pope; ſo that the Succeſſion of <hi>Christ's Kingdom</hi> cannot yet be The <hi>Kingdoms of this World;</hi> are not yet become the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of the Lord, and of his Chriſt.</hi> It is therefore very ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable, that Counterfeit of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> as it is a <hi>Mock Kingdom</hi> in regard of the Worldly Grandieur, of <hi>Popery, Cardinalls, Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, &amp;c.</hi> So it hath ſerved it ſelf of the Counterfeit of the <hi>Self Denial of the Goſpel</hi> in tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Auſtere, Self Denying Orders, under ſuch ſtrict Laws of Mortification,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:48863:15"/> and Deſpiſal of this World; Both Teaching us, if we would Learn; That there is indeed a Time of the Glory of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity in that Kingdom of Chriſt, but not Carnal and World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yet full of outward Glory, and Enjoyment; but that at the preſent All is in <hi>Patience</hi> and <hi>Affliction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. Every one ought at leaſt to look to this, to ſee, what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Secret Mortification, Self Examination, Humiliation, and profoundeſt Abaſement of Himſelf before God; Self Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation in Senſe of his own Unworthineſs, and manifold Tranſgreſſions, with all the Aggravations of Them; Self De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial, Holy Self-Reſignation, he Lives in the Practiſe, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of; laying our ſelves low at Chriſts Feet, bringing all the Glory to Chriſtianity, and bringing as many into it, as we can, <hi>Seeking not our own,</hi> but the <hi>Things that are Jeſus Chriſts. Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Affliction with the People of God in the State of our Minds;</hi> and Contributing All we can to the neceſſities of Saints; not <hi>Stretching our Selves, as on Beds of Ivory, Drinking Wine in Bowls, Chaunting to the Sound of the Viol and Organ, &amp;c. and forgetting the Afflictions of</hi> Joſeph; <hi>Waiting, Longing for the Kingdom and Appearance of Chriſt.</hi> If ſuch things as theſe are not in us, we are ſaving the Lives of a ſhort Figure, and looſing our <hi>Souls,</hi> and the <hi>Life Eternal</hi> that are for ever; we are in a <hi>Dream,</hi> and mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Image, God, and Chriſt will ſuddenly <hi>Awake,</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As a Concluſion, and as an Addition to the Second Head, I will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire into the meaning, and importance of that Vehement Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſignifying, that the loſs of a Soul cannot be ſlumbred away, <hi>What ſhall a man give in Exchange for his Soul?</hi> And it ſpeaks theſe three Things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Suppoſe that a Perſon could have the whole World in his Hand to give; <hi>It would be utterly Deſpiſed,</hi> It would be of no valew; This muſt needs be ſo; For if the World could be of value to <hi>Exchange</hi> for a <hi>Loſt Soul,</hi> It muſt then needs have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the <hi>Soul from being Loſt.</hi> For a Man therefore to come and ſay to God, here is the Eſtate I have gotten with the Loſs of my Soul, here is the Great Revenew I have attain'd, and left to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity; Here are the years I have ſpent in pleaſure, and that I was bleſſed upon Account of by all that lived about me, and Knew me; Becauſe I lived in Pomp and State, in All I could
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:48863:16"/> deſire, and did as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> Expreſſes it) well to my ſelf; will this, if it could be All given Back, be an Exchange for a Loſt Soul; no, the <hi>Redemption of Souls is precious,</hi> and <hi>Ceaſes for Ever,</hi> as to any ſuch <hi>Exchange;</hi> will the Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of it Appeaſe an Angry God, or as Enraged Conſcience? Alas, That will be the Burden, and ſting of that Condition; as the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> ſpeaks; <hi>Your Riches are Corrupted, and your Garments Moth-Faten, your Gold and Silver are Cankered, and the Rust of them ſhall witneſs againſt you, and eat your Fleſh, as it were Fire. You have heaped Treaſure together for the Laſt Days,</hi> James 5. 2, 3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Is there Any of the Creatures in Heaven or Earth, that can ſtretch out an Hand, or an Arm of Compaſſion in ſuch a caſe, as this is of a Loſt Soul? Are there any of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, of the higheſt Principalities in Heaven, the <hi>Thrones</hi> and <hi>Dominions</hi> there, that can ſtep in in a way of might, and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereſt Compaſſion, and ſay, Oh Soul, that art Loſt, now will I help, now will I Interpoſe, and bring thee off from thy Loſt State, and Reſcue thee? Or any of the Saints that have known the Temptations of Human Nature on Earth, or known any Particular Loſt Soul? Alas. This is all impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as it is ſaid in <hi>Job, Call now, if there be any that will Anſwer thee;</hi> and <hi>to which of the Saints wilt thou Turn? Job</hi> 5. 1. They all Juſtify, and Glorify the Righteous Judgment of God in that loſt State of the Perſon that hath undervalued his Soul; They praiſe the Mediator, by whom they themſelves Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, and the Redeemer, by whom they themſelves are Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled; They dare not appear Mediators, or Invade the Honour of the one Mediator, but as they Praiſe and Adore free Grace in Chriſt to themſelves, ſo they in Relation to thoſe Diſmal Appearances of the Loſt, as it is expreſſed in <hi>Ezekiel c.</hi> 14. 22. are <hi>Comforted in what God hath done, Beholding the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs with which he hath done it;</hi> when they ſee <hi>the ways and doings of Loſt Souls, and know that God hath not done without Cauſe All that he hath done unto them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. When the Saviour, and Redeemer of Souls ſhall ſay, <hi>What ſhall a Man Give in Exchange for his Loſt Soul?</hi> It is as if he ſhould ſay, Do not look that I ſhould be your Ranſom, your <hi>Exchange;</hi> that your <hi>Ruine ſhould be under my Hand,</hi> or I Reſcue you from it; While you were in the World, I offered
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:48863:16"/> you the wiſeſt of my Counſel, I offered you the deareſt and moſt precious of my Blood; And I ſaid with tears, Oh <hi>that in your day yau would have known the things of your peace, but now they are hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den from your eyes.</hi> I am now removed from being a Saviour to you, I am now altogether at a diſtance from you, or from ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you any compaſſion, as it is ſaid, <hi>Eſay</hi> 27. 11. <hi>They are a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of no underſtanding, therefore he that made them will not have mercy on them, and he that formed them will ſhew them no favour;</hi> So Chriſt will ſay, They have been ſouls of no conſideration, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all I have ſaid, therefore I have no Commiſſion from my Father, no Authority to interceed for <hi>theſe Children of perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> Only for thoſe he gave me, while in the World, I am no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer of loſt Souls on this other ſide of the Line of Life, and entred into Eternity.</p>
            <div type="applications">
               <p>Having now thus far inſiſted on this Point in a Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal way, I cloſe in brief with the particular Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Application </seg>1</label> I would ſpeak to the Atheiſt, that complains of the want of evidence and aſſurance of theſe things; I would ſpeak to him as in his own Language, and would, to diſcourſe with him ſay; There is not a certainty, I'll yield there is not ſuch a blockiſh, bruitiſh kind of certainty as he requires, that ſhould affect Stocks and Beaſts; yet I cannot but obſerve to him, that after all his cavil againſt evidence, he cannot get rid, or quit and clear of that he has; I dare appeal to him, whether his own Conſcience will not have the laſt word, that theſe things are ſo, however he be oblig'd not to confeſs it? But I would deal with him by way of proportion, upon our <hi>Saviour</hi>'s Words in ſuch a ſenſe as he will allow; That a man gets nothing, tho he ſhould gain the whole World, and <hi>loſe his life,</hi> in that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he gains it; I ask him in his way of certainty, What is that man the better? If then it be but poſſible, though not certain, there ſhould be a Soul to rue the loſs of it ſelf in a Chriſtian ſenſe; he knows what he can get; All is but ſuch a part of the World as he can get; it is but a World he hath nothing to do with when he dies; and there is this Bridle in his Jaws, do what he can, he cannot ſhake that off, he muſt die, he knows not how ſoon; and there remains a poſſibility of a Soul in a loſt ſtate, after all the World: What odds therefore does he give
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:48863:17"/> againſt himſelf in making nothing of a Soul, for a little of the World, in a Life, that cannot with all it has defray the charge of living, the <hi>vanity and vexation of Spirit</hi> that certainly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends Life; and the certainty it muſt end, and wholly uncertain how ſoon; and yet he ſtands the hazard of a Soul miſerable for ever, in its being loſt, and for ever crying out for an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change for it ſelf that cannot be found, any more than he knows what to give in exchange for his life, if once loſt. And why ſhould he, of all perſons, think a Soul miſerable for ever an impoſſible thing, tho not certain; or ſo much as improbable; that thinks ſo many things have been, and are, that no one, as he thinks, can tell how they come to be: Sure that man that will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve nothing but upon ſenſe, tranſgreſſes the very Law of his own Senſe, that ſees many things come to paſs, he look'd not for, and will not believe, becauſe he does not yet ſee; and againſt his own Prudentials upon Senſe; for he takes heed, and guards againſt things poſſible, that he has never ſeen yet by the eye of Senſe, why not then againſt this ſo dreadful proſſibility?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Application </seg>2</label> If it be ſo deſperate a caſe to <hi>loſe a ſoul</hi> for a <hi>whole world,</hi> how great madneſs is the loſs of a Soul for a little of the World? Men that live in Allyes and Dungeons, and <hi>eat in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs all their days,</hi> and y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t loſe their Souls; Oh how earneſt ſhould all the <hi>poor</hi> be to <hi>receive the Goſpel preached to them,</hi> as the moſt fit Subjects of it in that gracious Expreſſion of Chriſt to them, The <hi>poor are evangelized;</hi> and to lay hold on Eternal Life, to make a Vertue of that Neceſſity they are under. On the other ſide, they that live in gaiety and ſplendor, and value it ſo much, and have ſuch abhorring thoughts of a contrary condition, how ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ſhould they be to live ſo for ever, in a Divine Senſe, being receiv'd into the <hi>Inheritance of the Saints in Light,</hi> and not to fall into the miſeries of a <hi>loſt ſoul,</hi> as ſo horrible a deſcent from their preſent ſtate.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Application </seg>3</label> Let me beſeech you to take the things that have been conveyed to you in theſe Words, out of Words, and as things to weigh them well; for Things are greater than words, and canot be deceived, or turn'd off any more than Mountains, or Walls, or Gates of Iron and Braſs in our way: Let any one but for an hour think of theſe Words, he will find them riſe up to him as Things, and meet him with inward aſſurances; and ſo let
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:48863:17"/> him often do, and eſpecially with humbleſt ſupplication to the Father of Spirits, the Creator of Souls; through Chriſt the Lover and Redeemer of Souls; by the Spirit the bleſſed Inhabitant of all holy and wiſe Spirits; to impreſs upon him this great Oracle, concerning the value of Souls and Spirits; and he ſhall find by the Evidence, and witneſs within himſelf of the value of his own Soul, There is ſuch a ſenſe of theſe things poſſible to us, that he that hath <hi>loſt Houſes, Lands, Wife, Children</hi> for Chriſt's ſake may <hi>receive a hundred fold in this life,</hi> even now, and in the very midſt of <hi>Perſecution,</hi> (which is the greateſt evidence of their Reali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,) in the comforts and aſſurances of preſerving all unto Life E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal: For Chriſt adds; In the <hi>world to come life eternal, Mark</hi> 10. 29, 30.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Application </seg>4</label> Seeing things are ſo dark in the preſent ſmoak, black Vapour, thick Steam of this World, and the Luſts thereof; and are ſo hardly conſidered, and weighed duly, in the noiſes and duſt the rolling wheels of this World raiſe, Oh how earneſtly deſirous ſhould we be of that day dawning, <hi>that day of the Kingdom of Chriſt but dawning</hi> from on high, that ſhall make all theſe things ſo clear, as to put the World into another ſtate and poſture, as towards God, and all holineſs; and the more earneſt ſhould we be, ſeeing the day may by the <hi>ſure word of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſy ſhining</hi> in this <hi>dark place,</hi> be ſeen to be near approaching; and how great relation this great Saying of Chriſt hath to that Kingdom, appears, in that Chriſt goes on immediately to his coming in the Glory of his Kingdom, of which he gave a <hi>Type</hi> in the <hi>Transfiguration, Chap.</hi> 17. following.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THere is an Expoſition upon the whole Book of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> Explaining the Sacred <hi>Text</hi> Word by Word, and opening and arguing the Divine Senſes of that great <hi>Propheſy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sold by <hi>Richard Wellington</hi> at the Lute in St. <hi>Pauls Church-yard,</hi> and are to be had at Mr. <hi>Marſhals,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> in <hi>Newgate-ſtreet,</hi> and of Mr. <hi>Salisbury,</hi> at the <hi>Riſing-Sun</hi> in <hi>Corn-hill.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:48863:18"/>
            <head>Books Sold by <hi>VVilliam Marſhall,</hi> at the Bible in <hi>Newgate-Street.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Books Written by the late Dr. <hi>John Owen.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">In <hi>Folio.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. HIs Expoſition on the whole Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> with Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercitations concerning the <hi>Meſſiah?</hi> Wherein the Promiſes concerning him to be a Spiritual Redeemer of Mankind, are explained and vindicated. His Coming, and Accompliſhment of his Work according to the Promiſes, is proved and confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The Perſon, or who he is, declared. The whole Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy of the Moſaical Law, Rites, Worſhip and Sacrifices, is explained. And in all, the Doctine of the Perſon, Office, and Work of the Meſſiah, is opened: The Nature and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merit of the firſt Sin is unfolded: The Opinions and Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Antient and Modern Jews are examined: Their Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections againſt the Lord Chriſt and the Goſpel are anſwered: The time of the Coming of the Meſſiah is ſtated: And the great foundational Truth of the Goſpel vindicated. In four Volumes, <hi>Folio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A Diſcourſe concerning the <hi>Holy Spirit.</hi> Wherein an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it given of his Name, Nature, Perſonality, Diſpenſation, Operations, and Effects. His whole Work in the Old and New Creation is Explained: The Doctrine concerning it vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated from Oppoſitions and Reproaches. The Nature alſo and Neceſſity of Goſpel Holineſs; the Difference between Grace and Morality, or a Spiritual Life unto God in Evangelical O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and a Courſe of Moral Virtues, are ſtated and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared. <hi>Fol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Doctrine of the <hi>Saints Perſeverance,</hi> explained and confirmed. Or, the certain Permanency of their (1.) Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation with God; and (2.) Sanctification from God; manifeſted and proved: From, 1. The Eternal Principles, 2. The Effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ual Cauſes: And, 3. The External Means thereof, <hi>&amp;c. Fol.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:48863:18"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
